so i finished learning how to make an
fps controller but if i want to make a
more polished looking game i will need
to work on my environment and since i'm
more of a coder than an artist i think
there's no better way than with
procedural generation
[Music]
so let's begin by starting a new project
next it's time to go on my usual youtube
grind and figure out how to do mesh
generation thankfully brackis has three
videos on this topic three days later
after watching bracki's videos i'm now
able to generate meshes of any size that
i need and all it took is the code you
see on the left now to make this look
like terrain use something called purlin
noise which is an algorithm created by
ken perlin to help make more natural
looking textures and terrain on the
movie tron what i'm using here is the 2d
version which generates values between 0
and 1. to represent this i map the
numbers closer to 0 as black and numbers
closer to 1 is white the power of this
algorithm comes and you multiply that
prelim value by a number for instance i
can use parallel noise multiplied by an
amplitude to procedurally generate the
height of my terrain
this is all fine and dandy but i wanted
a little bit more control over my
environment thankfully i found this
tutorial series by sebastian lake and it
covered everything i wanted to know and
more it seriously was so good that i
gave it a watch a few times over the
problem is it goes into so much depth
that is too comprehensive for my puny
brain to handle so i took two of the
simpler concepts to add to my generator
one was the ability to finally tune the
noise and two was this concept of
multiplying the purlin noise with the
falloff map to create islands i actually
wrote my own version of sebastian's
fallout map so that i could set where
the falloff begins and ends here's a
preview of that code for those of you
who are interested i also fixed
sebastian's noise generator because i
think he broke it around episode 6 and
then never fixed it when you change the
scale you're supposed to be able to zoom
in and out of the berlin map but right
now it almost seems like you're
generating a new map i narrowed down the
problem to these lines here
changing this also fixed the parallax
effect sebastian had when changing the
offset
now that we have more control over our
environment it's time to move on to my
favorite topic from elementary school
and that is coloring
so for coloring i spent about a week or
two trying to recreate the style
sebastian had for his intro he shows
that he's generating a texture with
these nicely rounded edges but in the
tutorials he only teaches us how to make
a pixelated texture one solution i had
was to increase the number of sample
points we use in the texture but if you
zoom in we still have the problem of
seeing each individual pixel then i
remembered watching a video by sebastian
where he used marching cubes and i was
almost certain this is the approach he
used for generating his texture so i
watched this video by the coding train
and converted his marching squares
algorithm from javascript into c sharp i
got pretty close to the results i wanted
but when you view this on the terrain
you could still see each individual
pixel
so i gave up on using a texture approach
i really tried to avoid this as much as
i could but i was left with no other
choice but to dive into shaders
after messing with shader graph for a
few hours i came up with this decent
shader here i surprisingly had a lot of
fun making this and it turns out shaders
aren't too hard after all with my new
love for shaders i looked up a bunch of
more tutorials on youtube i found this
tutorial for creating a gradient skybox
with stars but i noticed there's a
little bit of distortion near the edges
so i found this article that taught me
how to do proper uv sphere projection
and yay no more distortion
but i wasn't quite satisfied yet i also
found this awesome cloud shader that i
needed to use as well and now our skies
are looking not too bad
then to top it all off i use these two
videos to make a stylized water
alright let's finish off this last bit
here so to finish off this project let's
add some vegetation i hopped in the
blender and made this very beginner
friendly tree but i don't want to
manually place hundreds of trees on the
terrain because that would take forever
and we are going for a complete
procedural generation thankfully i
remember watching this video from jonas
tyroller a while back where he talked
about creating random levels for his
game islander basically if you shoot a
raycast onto a random point on the
island you can check if it's a valid
spawn point for a tree if so spawn the
tree then you can do this for as many
times as you want trees or whatever
object you want to randomly place so i
created this simple prefab spawner
script where i can select a prefab to
spawn then to determine if a spot is
valid to place a prefab i just check if
the hit location is above the sea level
i also have the script randomly change
the scale and rotation of the prefab we
are spawning so that we have a bit of
variation lastly let's add some grass i
found this video to create a quick grass
texture then i put together a bunch of
planes in blender to display it back in
unity i just reused my prefabs
manuscript to spawn my grass around the
island
although to really bring this grass to
life i watched this video from bradku's
and now we have sway in our grass
[Music]
so i brought over my fps controller from
the last video so that we can explore
the island and after working on this for
so long it's super cool to see this from
the first person view with what we have
here it's really starting to feel like a
really polished game the sky the water
with fps movements everything ties
nicely together to really bring that
to be honest i could keep on going and
continue to add things to my procedure
generator but then this video will never
end i definitely will be working on this
tool in future videos and i am just so
pleased with how much i was able to
figure out this is definitely going to
help me out in any future game that i
make and even just this island already
feels like a cool spot to do 1v1 death
matches on i can imagine doing some sick
multiplayer battles on here finding good
angles to pick off people on the island
but anyways if you stuck around this
long thank you so much for watching and
i hope to see you in the next one peace